<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">16</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">bmccanc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2407</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12670725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12670725.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12670725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12670725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41316051</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-025-15352-w</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">15352</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comprehensive analysis of gene expression alterations in breast cancer patients via PKC&#952;-TBK1-mTORC1 signaling pathway</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hafeez</surname><given-names initials="A">Amna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basit</surname><given-names initials="M">Mahnoor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names initials="S">Sameen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabbir</surname><given-names initials="M">Maria</given-names></name><address><email>mshabbir@asab.nust.edu.pk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badshah</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yasmin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trembley</surname><given-names initials="JH">Janeen H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Afsar</surname><given-names initials="T">Tayyaba</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names initials="A">Altaf</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razak</surname><given-names initials="S">Suhail</given-names></name><address><email>smarazi@ksu.edu.sa</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03w2j5y17</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412117.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2234 2376</institution-id><institution>Department of Biomedicine, Atta-Ur-Rahman School of Applied Biosciences (ASAB), </institution><institution>National University of Sciences and Technology (NUST), </institution></institution-wrap>Sector H-12, Islamabad, 44000 Pakistan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02ry60714</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410394.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0419 8667</institution-id><institution>Minneapolis VA Health Care System Research Service, </institution></institution-wrap>Minneapolis, MN USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/017zqws13</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.17635.36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8657</institution-id><institution>Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, </institution><institution>University of Minnesota, </institution></institution-wrap>Minneapolis, MN USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/017zqws13</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.17635.36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000419368657</institution-id><institution>Masonic Cancer Centre, </institution><institution>University of Minnesota, </institution></institution-wrap>Minneapolis, MN USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02f81g417</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.56302.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 5396</institution-id><institution>Department of Community Health Sciences, College of Applied Medical Sciences, </institution><institution>King Saud University, </institution></institution-wrap>Riyadh, Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02f81g417</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.56302.32</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 5396</institution-id><institution>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, College of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>King Saud University, </institution></institution-wrap>Riyadh, 11433 Saudi Arabia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478185</issue-id><elocation-id>1844</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-12-03 10:25:12.827"><day>03</day><month>12</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12885_2025_Article_15352.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Breast cancer remains a leading cause of cancer-related mortality among women globally. The emergence of chemoresistance and the lack of early detection tools necessitate the identification of reliable molecular biomarkers and therapeutic targets. Protein kinase C theta (PRKCQ/PKC&#952;), a serine/threonine kinase, has been implicated in immune signaling and cancer. The current study was designed to investigate the relative expression levels of PRKCQ and its downstream components, including TANK-binding kinase 1 (TBK1), mammalian target of rapamycin (mTORC1), ribosomal S6 kinase (S6K), Jun Proto-Oncogene (JUNB), and the tumor suppressor gene p21, in breast cancer. The study also aimed to evaluate their association with key clinicopathological features.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Gene expression analysis was conducted using quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) on breast cancer blood samples. Expression levels were compared between breast cancer patients and healthy controls, and further analyzed to metastasis, cancer stage, histological subtype, molecular classification, family history, BRCA status, menopausal status, and lactation history.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Expression of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, and JUNB was significantly upregulated in breast cancer blood samples compared to controls, whereas p21 expression was downregulated. Statistically significant associations were observed between gene expression levels and various clinicopathological parameters. Notably, PRKCQ showed strong differential expression across molecular subtypes with the highest expression in TNBC. A signaling axis involving PRKCQ&#8211;TBK1&#8211;mTORC1&#8211;S6K and an independent PRKCQ-JUNB-VEGFR axis was proposed.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">The relative expression of PRKCQ and its associated signaling components suggests their critical role in breast cancer progression. These molecules, especially PRKCQ, may serve as potential biomarkers for early detection and prognosis, as well as targets for therapeutic intervention following further validation.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12885-025-15352-w.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Cancer</kwd><kwd>PRKCQ</kwd><kwd>Biomarkers</kwd><kwd>Molecular Docking</kwd><kwd>Breast cancer</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Breast cancer remains one of the most prevalent and deadly malignancies among women worldwide. Accounting for approximately 11.6% of all female cancers, it is the second most diagnosed cancer globally and contributes to nearly 6% of total cancer-related mortalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The disease typically originates from the epithelial lining of milk ducts or lobules and is characterized by uncontrolled cell proliferation and the formation of palpable masses in breast tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. While early diagnosis and improved treatment strategies have significantly enhanced the five-year survival rate in developed countries, the prognosis in low- and middle-income regions remains poor due to late-stage detection and limited therapeutic options. Additionally, the development of resistance to standard therapies continues to pose a major challenge in breast cancer management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">PRKCQ, encoding the protein kinase C theta PKC&#952;, a serine/threonine kinase predominantly expressed in T cells, has also been found to play an oncogenic role in various solid tumors by regulating cell survival and inflammatory signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Despite its emerging relevance in cancer biology, its involvement in breast cancer-specific signaling pathways remains poorly characterized. Emerging studies suggest that therapy resistance and tumor progression are often driven by abnormal activation of signaling pathways that control cell growth and survival. One such signaling cascade involves the interaction of PKC&#952; (PRKCQ), TANK-binding kinase 1 (TBK1), and the mammalian target of rapamycin (mTORC1), which collectively influence downstream effectors like ribosomal S6 kinase (S6K) and mTORC1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Recent studies have highlighted the role of PKC&#952; in regulating angiogenic and transcriptional responses via JunB. In hypoxia-mediated retinal neovascularization, VEGFA signaling induces phosphorylation of PKC&#952;, which subsequently upregulates JunB expression, leading to increased VEGFR3 transcription and angiogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. This mechanism emphasizes the function of PKC&#952; as an upstream regulator of JunB-driven transcriptional programs that facilitate cellular migration and vascular remodeling. Given the parallels between angiogenic signaling in retinal tissue and tumor microenvironments, these findings support the hypothesis that PRKCQ may contribute to breast cancer progression through a similar JunB-mediated pathway. Based on gene expression profiles, breast cancer is broadly divided into Luminal A, Luminal B, HER2-enriched, and Triple-Negative/Basal-like (TNBC) subtypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Luminal A and B tumors are typically hormone receptor&#8211;positive and generally have a better prognosis, whereas HER2-enriched and TNBC subtypes are more aggressive and often associated with poorer clinical outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Histologically, the most common forms include Invasive Ductal Carcinoma (IDC), Invasive Lobular Carcinoma (ILC), and mixed IDC/ILC, which differ in their cellular morphology and invasive behavior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The current study aims to evaluate the relative expression patterns of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, JUNB, and p21 in breast cancer samples compared to controls. Furthermore, it investigates the association of these genes with key clinicopathological features, including tumor stage, histological and molecular subtypes, and family history of cancer. Evaluating the expression of key regulatory genes across breast cancer subtypes is important to identify potential subtype-specific molecular signatures and clarify their roles in breast cancer progression. By characterizing these molecular alterations, the study seeks to better understand their contributions to breast cancer progression and identify potential targets for future therapeutic intervention.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Blood sample collection</title><p id="Par7">This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB No. 2024-IRB-A-14/14) of the Atta-ur-Rahman School of Applied Biosciences (ASAB), National University of Sciences and Technology (NUST). Informed consent was obtained from all study participants. Blood samples were collected from histopathologically confirmed breast cancer patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 100) patients at hospitals in Islamabad and Rawalpindi, Pakistan. Individuals with known co-infections such as HIV or other chronic conditions including cardiovascular, neurological, or metabolic disorders were excluded from participation. Healthy individuals (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 100) with no history of malignancy were included as controls. The study was conducted in accordance with the ethical principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis</title><p id="Par8">Total RNA was extracted from whole blood samples using the TRIzol reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) following the manufacturer&#8217;s guidelines. For each participant, 4 mL of peripheral whole blood was collected in EDTA tubes, and 500 &#181;L of each sample was used for RNA extraction according to the optimized protocol for this study. All procedures were carried out on ice to minimize RNA degradation and RNA quantity and purity were assessed using a NanoDrop&#8482; spectrophotometer. cDNA synthesis was performed in a total reaction volume of 20&#160;&#181;l using the RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Scientific), as per the kit protocol.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title><p id="Par9">Gene expression levels of selected targets, including PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, JUNB, and p21, were quantified using SYBR&#8482; Green-based qRT-PCR. The reaction mixture (20&#160;&#181;l total volume) consisted of SYBR&#8482; Green PCR Master Mix (Thermo Fisher Scientific), specific primers, and synthesized cDNA. Reactions were run on the Applied Biosystems StepOne Real-Time PCR System. All samples were analyzed in triplicate to ensure reproducibility. Relative gene expression was calculated using the 2-&#916;&#916;CT method, where the cycle threshold (Ct) value was converted to fold-change using the Livak method, with GAPDH serving as the endogenous control. The primers used for each gene are given in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par10">
<table-wrap id="Tab1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sequences of primers used for qRT-PCR</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gene</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Primers</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">PRKCQ</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AAATTGTCAAGATAGAAAAGATAGTAT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CTAGATGGCAAGGGTGAAATG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TBK1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AGCGGCAGAGTTAGGTGAAA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCAGTGATCCACCTGGAGAT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">mTORC1C1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">AGTGGACCAGTGGAAACAGG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CAGTTCAGACCAGCAGGACA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">S6K</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CATGGGGGAGTTGGACCATA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GCCCCCTTTACCAAGTACCC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">JUNB</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CGCCGACGGCTTTGT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGTGTCACGTGGTTC</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">p21</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Forward</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">GGACCTGGAGACTCTCA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CCTCTTGGAGAAGATCAG</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par11">Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism software version 8.4.2. One-way ANOVA was applied to evaluate differences in gene expression across various clinicopathological features, including disease stage, histological subtype, molecular classification, and family history. Two-way ANOVA was performed using Dunnett&#8217;s multiple comparisons test to compare patient groups with healthy controls. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Pathway construction</title><p id="Par12">To explore the upstream and downstream regulatory elements of PRKCQ and assess the gene-gene interactions among the studied targets, several in silico tools were utilized. Functional associations were examined using databases such as STRING [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and the KEGG (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes) pathway repository [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. A genetic network was developed to visualize the crosstalk between PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, JUNB, and p21. The constructed pathway was further supported through a comprehensive literature review.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results</title><p id="Par13">One hundred breast cancer patients and 100 healthy controls were used in this study. The clinicopathological characteristics of the breast cancer patients included in this study are summarized in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. These features encompass age, molecular subtypes based on receptor status, tumor histology, metastatic classification, clinical staging, family history, lactation status, and menopausal status.</p><p id="Par14">
<table-wrap id="Tab2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Clinicopathological characteristics of breast cancer patients included in the study, based on age, molecular subtypes (defined by receptor status and Ki67 index), histological types, metastatic status, disease stage, family history, lactation status, and menopausal status</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BC clinical Features</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Details</th><th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;&#8201;45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&gt;&#8201;45</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Receptor Status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Luminal A (ER&#8201;+, PR&#8201;+, HER2-, Ki67 index low)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Luminal B (ER&#8201;+, PR&#8201;+, HER2-/+, Ki67 index high)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">HER2 Positive</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">TNBC (ER-, PR-, HER2-)</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Molecular Type</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IDC</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">LCIS</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Mixed</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Metastatic Status</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-metastatic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Metastatic</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Stages</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage 1</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage 2</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage 3</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Stage 4</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Family History</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Family History</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">No Family History</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Lactation</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Lactating</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Non-lactating</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">87</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Menopause</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pre-menopause</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Post-menopause</td><td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">37</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><sec id="Sec9"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in breast cancer patients</title><p id="Par15">In the blood of breast cancer patients, PRKCQ expression was evaluated along with five cancer-related genes involved in cellular signaling and regulatory pathways potentially interacting with PRKCQ (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Among these, PRKCQ expression was markedly elevated in patients, showing a 6.49&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.33.-fold increase compared to controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0012). Similarly, TBK1 levels were 5.33&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.36-fold higher in the patient group, a statistically significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0023). A substantial upregulation was also observed for mTORC1, whose expression increased by 17.68&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.43-fold in cancer samples relative to controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0002). The expression of S6K was significantly higher in breast cancer patients, showing a 5.68&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.33-fold increase over controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0016). JUNB expression was also notably raised by 1.99&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.33-fold in the patient group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0054). In contrast, p21 expression was significantly downregulated in cancer patients, showing a 0.68&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.07-fold decrease relative to controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0197). These differences underline the potential involvement of these genes in breast cancer pathogenesis.</p><p id="Par16">
<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Relative mRNA expression of a PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 in the blood of breast cancer patients compared to healthy controls. Gene expression is represented as fold change from experiments performed in triplicate. Two-way ANOVA was used to assess statistical significance</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e673" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in metastatic breast cancer patients</title><p id="Par17">To further evaluate the clinical relevance of these genes in breast cancer progression, their relative expression was assessed based on metastatic status. The comparison was conducted among control, non-metastatic, and metastatic patient groups using one-way ANOVA followed by Dunnett&#8217;s post hoc test (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). PRKCQ expression showed a statistically significant and progressive increase with disease advancement. It was 2.60&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.53-fold higher in non-metastatic samples (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0081) and peaked at 5.33&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.53-fold in metastatic patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) compared to controls. mTORC1 exhibited the most substantial increase, with an 18.62&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.27-fold upregulation in non-metastatic and a 25.27&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.85-fold increase in metastatic patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), highlighting its robust association with tumor aggressiveness. TBK1 and S6K also followed this trend, with TBK1 rising 4.46&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.85-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0023) in non-metastatic cases and 7.78&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.87-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) in metastatic samples, and S6K showing 4.46&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.47-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) in non-metastatic and 7.88&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.32-fold increases (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) in metastatic patients. JUNB expression was moderately elevated in both groups, showing a 2.00&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.26-fold increase in non-metastatic samples (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0055), which slightly declined in metastatic patients (1.66&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.35-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0340), possibly indicating a shift in transcriptional dynamics during metastasis. p21 showed a significant reduction in expression. The greatest downregulation was seen in the non-metastatic group (0.47&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.05-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), followed by the metastatic group (0.67&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.05-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0002) compared to controls. This decline supports its role in the loss of cell cycle regulation.</p><p id="Par18">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Association of <bold>a</bold>: PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 mRNA expression with metastatic status of breast cancer. The fold change represents the mean of experiments performed in triplicates. Statistical significance was determined using one-way ANOVA (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, ****<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e757" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in breast cancer stages</title><p id="Par19">To evaluate the clinical relevance of these genes in breast cancer progression, we analyzed their relative expression across different clinical stages (I&#8211;IV) using one-way ANOVA (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). PRKCQ expression showed a statistically significant and progressive increase with cancer stage, reaching its peak in Stage IV compared to controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Similarly, TBK1 expression increased consistently across stages, with the highest expression observed in Stage III (5.72&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.68-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). mTORC1 also exhibited a stage-dependent upregulation in Stage II, III, and IV, respectively, with all differences being highly significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). S6K expression followed a similar pattern, showing the greatest elevation in Stage III (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), while Stage I samples exhibited a modest increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0465). JUNB expression was significantly upregulated in Stage I (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0004), Stage II (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0008), and Stage III (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0096). In contrast, p21 showed a variable and significantly downregulated expression across all stages relative to control: Stage I (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), Stage II, (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0076), Stage III (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), and Stage IV (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0196).</p><p id="Par20">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Association of <bold>a</bold>: PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 mRNA expression with stages of breast cancer. The fold change represents the mean from experiments performed in triplicate. One-way ANOVA was employed to determine statistical significance (***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001; ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e844" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in histological subtypes of breast cancer</title><p id="Par21">The relative expression of PRKCQ, S6K, TBK1, mTORC1, JUNB, and p21 was analyzed in breast cancer patients with different histological subtypes, IDC, ILC, and Mixed IDC and ILC (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). PRKCQ was upregulated by 5.6&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.77-fold in ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) and 4.7&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.28-fold in mixed IDC/ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), whereas no significant change was observed in the IDC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.4807). TBK1 expression showed significant upregulation in all three subtypes. The highest increase was observed in ILC compared to controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), followed by mixed IDC/ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), and IDC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0006). mTORC1 expression was markedly elevated across all tumor types. It was 31&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.40-fold higher in ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), 16.5&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.94-fold higher in IDC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), and 5.9&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.99-fold higher in mixed IDC/ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0008), indicating mTORC1 pathway activation, especially in the lobular subtype. S6K expression varied significantly across subtypes. A strong upregulation was seen in ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), and a moderate increase in mixed IDC/ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0145). In contrast, the increase in IDC was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0692). JUNB expression was significantly upregulated for ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0005), mixed IDC/ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0015), and IDC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0033). p21 showed significant downregulation across all subtypes mixed IDC/ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), ILC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), and in IDC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0376).</p><p id="Par22">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Association of (<bold>a</bold>) PRKCQ, (<bold>b</bold>) TBK1, (<bold>c</bold>) mTORC1, (<bold>d</bold>) S6K, (<bold>e</bold>) JUNB, and (<bold>f</bold>) p21 mRNA expression with histological subtypes of breast cancer. The fold change represents the mean from experiments performed in triplicate. One-way ANOVA was employed to determine statistical significance (**** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001; *** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001; ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01; * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e950" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in molecular subtypes of breast cancer</title><p id="Par23">To assess the potential subtype-specific roles of the selected genes, their expression profiles were evaluated in molecular subtypes of breast cancer (Luminal A, Luminal B, HER2-positive, and TNBC) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). PRKCQ expression was markedly upregulated in all subtypes compared to the control group. The highest expression was observed in TNBC, showing a 7.59&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.71-fold increase, followed by Luminal B (6.01&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.29-fold), Luminal A (5.67&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.75-fold), and HER2+ (2.99&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.23-fold). Similarly, TBK1 and mTORC1 expression increased across all molecular classes, with the most pronounced elevation in TNBC, followed by Luminal B, Luminal A, and HER2+. S6K showed significant overexpression in Luminal B (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) and TNBC (6.99-fold), while Luminal A (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) and HER2+ (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0006) were also significantly elevated (In contrast, JUNB expression was only modestly elevated. The highest expression was noted in Luminal B (2.09-fold&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.71) and TNBC (1.81-fold&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.13), with less elevation in HER2+ (1.40-fold&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.13) and Luminal A (1.25-fold&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.05). Interestingly, p21 expression showed subtype-specific trends: a strong downregulation in TNBC (0.26&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.11-fold), slight downregulation in Luminal B (0.70-fold&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.05), and non-significant changes in Luminal A and HER2+.</p><p id="Par24">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Association of <bold>a</bold>: PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 mRNA expression with molecular subtypes of breast cancer. The fold change represents the mean from experiments performed in triplicate. One-way ANOVA was applied to determine statistical significance. (****<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001; ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1008" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in patients with family history of breast cancer</title><p id="Par25">The expression of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, JUNB, and p21 was analyzed based on family history status of breast cancer patients between patients with a positive family history and those without (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). PRKCQ expression was substantially higher in negative family history patients, showing a 11.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.85-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) increase relative to positive family history cases. TBK1 expression also exhibited a slight elevation in the negative family history group, with a 5.1&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.21-fold increase compared to those individuals with positive family history of breast cancer. mTORC1 levels were highly elevated in patients with a negative family history, relative to the positive family history group. S6K followed the same trend with a 5.70&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.31 -fold increase in patients without a family history of breast cancer. JUNB expression was also significantly upregulated in the negative family history group, albeit to a lesser extent. p21 was significantly downregulated in those with a positive family history, with expression reduced to 0.54&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.09-fold of the levels seen in patients with a familial background.</p><p id="Par26">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Association of <bold>a</bold>: PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 mRNA expression with family history of breast cancer. The fold change represents the mean of experiments performed in triplicates. Statistical significance was determined using one-way ANOVA (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, ****<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1060" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in BRCA-Mutated breast cancer patients</title><p id="Par27">To assess whether BRCA mutation status influences oncogenic and tumor suppressor signaling, the relative expression levels of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTOR, S6K, JUNB, and p21 were compared across BRCA-positive, BRCA-negative, and control samples (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Among the genes examined, PRKCQ expression was significantly elevated in both BRCA-positive and BRCA-negative patients compared to controls, with a more pronounced increase in BRCA-positive individuals (4.74&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.59-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0001 vs. 3.42&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.55-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0013). Similarly associated genes, including TBK1, mTOR, S6K and JUNB, were markedly upregulated in BRCA-positive samples, with TBK1 showing a 6.19&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.0-fold increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0004), mTOR a 22.19&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.61 -fold increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), S6K a 10.31&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.0-fold increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) and JUNB a 2.03&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.47 -fold increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0073). While expression levels of these genes were also elevated in BRCA-negative patients, the magnitude and statistical significance were comparatively lower. In contrast, p21 was significantly downregulated in both groups, with BRCA-positive patients exhibiting a stronger decrease (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) compared to BRCA-negative patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0426).</p><p id="Par28">
<fig id="Fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Association of <bold>a</bold>: PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 mRNA expression with menopausal status in breast cancer patients. The fold change represents the mean of experiments performed in triplicates. Statistical significance was determined using one-way ANOVA (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, ****<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1134" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig7_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in pre- and post-menopausal breast cancer patients</title><p id="Par29">To explore the influence of menopausal status on oncogenic signaling in breast cancer, we assessed the expression levels of PRKCQ and its downstream targets in pre- and post-menopausal patient groups (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). PRKCQ expression was significantly upregulated in both groups, in pre-menopausal (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) and in post-menopausal patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0021) compared to controls. Among downstream effectors, the most pronounced changes were observed in the pre-menopausal group. mTOR showed 26.74&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.94-fold elevation (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), accompanied by significantly increased expression of TBK1 (6.70&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.4-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0004), S6K (6.13&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.42 -fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), and JUNB (1.55 0.24 -fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0224). In contrast, while these genes were also significantly upregulated in post-menopausal patients, the magnitude of change was comparatively lower. Tumor suppressor p21 was notably reduced in both groups, with a greater decrease observed in pre-menopausal patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0002) than in post-menopausal ones (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0243).</p><p id="Par30">
<fig id="Fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Association of <bold>a</bold>: PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 mRNA expression with BRCA mutation status in breast cancer patients. The fold change represents the mean of experiments performed in triplicates. Statistical significance was determined using one-way ANOVA (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, ****<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1208" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig8_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>Relative expression of PRKCQ and associated genes in lactating and non-lactating breast cancer patients</title><p id="Par31">To assess the impact of lactation status on gene expression in breast cancer, mRNA levels of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTOR, S6K, JUNB, and p21 were analyzed in lactating and non-lactating patients compared to healthy controls using one-way ANOVA (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). PRKCQ expression was significantly elevated in both lactating and non-lactating breast cancer patients, with non-lactating patients showing a greater increase (4.99&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.73-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0006) compared to lactating patients (3.80&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.87-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0035). Among downstream effectors, mTOR exhibited the highest differential expression, with a dramatic 36.64&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.0-fold increase in lactating patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). Similarly, TBK1, S6K, and JUNB also showed significantly higher expression, particularly in the non-lactating group, with TBK1 upregulated by 5.83&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.15-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0007), S6K by 5.95&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.95-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0001), and JUNB by 1.81&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.14-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). p21 was significantly downregulated in both subgroups, with a sharper decline in lactating patients (0.33&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.07-fold <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) compared to non-lactating patients (0.76&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.06-fold, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0044).</p><p id="Par32">
<fig id="Fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Association of <bold>a</bold>: PRKCQ, <bold>b</bold>: TBK1, <bold>c</bold>: mTORC1, <bold>d</bold>: S6K, <bold>e</bold>: JUNB, and <bold>f</bold>: p21 mRNA expression with lactation status in breast cancer patients. The fold change represents the mean of experiments performed in triplicates. Statistical significance was determined using one-way ANOVA (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1282" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig9_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Pathway construction</title><p id="Par33">According to the findings of this study and supported by analyses from KEGG, STRING, (Supplementary Figs. 1 and 2) and existing literature, PRKCQ (PKC&#952;), TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, JUNB, and p21 are functionally interconnected in an oncogenic signaling axis through growth factors (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). PKC&#952; acts upstream of TBK1 and phosphorylates it via recruitment by the adaptor TBKBP1 and the scaffold protein CARD10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Activated TBK1 directly associates with Raptor, a subunit of the mTORC1 complex, which subsequently stimulates S6K phosphorylation, enhancing tumor cell proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The role of PKC&#952; in regulating angiogenic responses via JunB and VEGFR is also shown. The constructed pathway also reflects the observed suppression of the tumor suppressor p21 (CDKN1A). Reduced p21 levels eliminate critical cell cycle checkpoints, further promoting tumorigenesis.</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Pathway showing crosstalk between PKC&#952;, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, JUNB, and p21</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1309" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_Fig10_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par35">In this study, we explored the expression profiles of key genes implicated in breast cancer pathogenesis, including PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, JUNB, and the tumor suppressor p21. Our analyses compared gene expression levels between breast cancer patients and healthy controls and further analyzed expression patterns based on clinicopathological features such as metastasis, cancer stage, histological subtype, molecular classification, family history, BRCA status, menopausal status, and lactation history. These genes were selected based on their interconnected roles in oncogenic signaling pathways, particularly the PRKCQ&#8211;TBK1&#8211;mTORC1&#8211;S6K axis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] and the PRKCQ-mediated regulation of AP-1 transcription factor JUNB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Our findings revealed that all genes involved in the proposed PRKCQ&#8211;TBK1&#8211;mTORC1&#8211;S6K signaling cascade were significantly upregulated in breast cancer patients compared to healthy controls. Specifically, comparing all breast cancer with health control patient circulating gene expression levels, mTORC1 exhibited the highest mean fold change followed by PRKCQ, TBK1 and S6K. These results are consistent with the established role of these genes in promoting tumor growth and proliferation through the mTORC1 pathway. Prior studies have demonstrated that TBK1 is activated by growth factors in a PKC&#952; (PRKCQ)-dependent manner and facilitates mTORC1 activation via interaction with Raptor, a component of mTORC1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Our data further supports this pathway, as PRKCQ overexpression coincided with elevated TBK1 and mTORC1 levels, indicating coordinated activation of this oncogenic axis in breast cancer patients. The expression of JUNB was moderately upregulated, while p21, a known tumor suppressor, was significantly downregulated in breast cancer patients relative to controls. These observations reinforce the notion that PRKCQ may not only drive oncogenic signaling via the mTORC1 pathway but also modulate transcriptional responses through JUNB, a component of the AP-1 transcription factor. Previous studies suggest that PRKCQ may regulate AP-1 at the transcriptional level in response to growth factor signals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The upregulation of JUNB observed in our patient cohort may thus be partially attributed to this route. The downregulation of p21, a cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor, is consistent with its tumor-suppressive role [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and further underscores the proliferative nature of the molecular environment in breast cancer.</p><p id="Par36">To determine whether these genes correlate with metastatic potential, we analyzed their expression in metastatic and non-metastatic breast cancer samples. A statistically significant elevation in the expression of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, and S6K was observed in metastatic tumors compared to controls. Specifically, PRKCQ expression increased by 2.60&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.53-fold in non-metastatic (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0081) and 5.33&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.53-fold in metastatic patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001). TBK1 expression rose by 4.46&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.85-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0023) in non-metastatic cases and 7.78&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.87-fold (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001) in metastatic samples, reflecting a possible role in driving tumor aggressiveness. mTORC1 showed marked increases, 18.62&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.27-fold upregulation in non-metastatic and a 25.27&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.85-fold increase in metastatic patients (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001), The downstream effector S6K also followed similar pattern. This elevation supports the idea that the PRKCQ&#8211;TBK1&#8211;mTOR&#8211;S6K signaling axis may be progressively activated in more aggressive disease states. When examining clinicopathological features, we observed a marked upregulation of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, and S6K in advanced-stage tumors compared to early-stage tumors. For instance, PRKCQ expression was higher in advanced-stage tumors, while mTORC1 and TBK1 showed significantly elevated expression across all high-grade subgroups. This aligns with the previously established role of the TBK1&#8211;mTORC1 axis in sustaining tumor growth in response to growth factors, which are often more abundant or dysregulated in aggressive tumor types. Similarly, JUNB was significantly upregulated in later stages, supporting its contribution to enhanced proliferation and AP-1&#8211;mediated transcriptional programs during tumor progression.</p><p id="Par37">Histological subtype analysis revealed the highest expression of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, and S6K in ILC, followed by mixed IDC/ILC, and then IDC. These patterns suggest a potential histotype-specific enrichment of the PRKCQ&#8211;TBK1&#8211;mTORC1 signaling activity, particularly in ILC, which may guide future subtype-targeted therapeutic strategies. JUNB expression also followed this trend, with highest levels in ILC and mixed IDC/ILC, consistent with the known activation of AP-1 components in invasive breast cancers. Across molecular subtypes, all four genes were significantly upregulated in TNBC, followed by Luminal B, Luminal A, and HER2+. TNBC exhibited the most aggressive expression profiles: PRKCQ was upregulated 7.59 &#177; 0.71-fold compared to controls. These findings emphasize the potential role of this pathway in aggressive and treatment-resistant subtypes such as TNBC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The heightened activation of JUNB in TNBC further supports the involvement of the AP-1 pathway in driving the proliferative phenotype of these tumors. Meanwhile, p21 expression was lowest in TNBC. Although literature reports elevated or context-dependent expression of p21 in breast cancer, studies have also documented its downregulation in TNBC and other aggressive subtypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. These discrepancies may arise from differences in tumor heterogeneity, p53 mutation status, sample source and stage-specific regulation of p21. The dual role of p21 in both tumor suppression and survival signaling could contribute to these contrasting observations.</p><p id="Par38">We also analyzed the expression patterns based on family history. All genes in the pathway showed significantly higher expression in patients with a negative family history, suggesting that genetic predisposition may not be associated with stronger activation of this oncogenic signaling cascade. Notably, PRKCQ, mTORC1, and TBK1 showed markedly elevated expression in this subgroup, indicating that non-hereditary breast cancers might preferentially utilize this pathway for tumor development. BRCA-positive patients exhibited significantly higher expression of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, and JUNB, with a concurrent downregulation of p21, suggesting enhanced reliance on this oncogenic axis and reduced tumor suppressive activity. Similarly, pre-menopausal patients showed stronger activation of PRKCQ&#8211;TBK1&#8211;mTORC1&#8211;S6K, while JUNB expression was more pronounced in post-menopausal cases, possibly reflecting compensatory transcriptional activity. Across both groups, p21 remained suppressed. Lactation status also influenced expression, non-lactating patients demonstrated higher levels of TBK1, S6K, and JUNB than lactating ones, though both groups showed significant activation of the pathway and downregulation of p21. Collectively, these findings indicate that reproductive and genetic factors modulate the intensity of this signaling cascade in breast cancer. To complement the transcriptomic findings, in-silico analyses using the STRING and KEGG databases were performed to explore potential molecular interactions and enriched signaling pathways among the studied genes. The STRING protein&#8211;protein interaction (PPI) network revealed significant functional associations among PRKCQ, TBK1, MTOR, RPS6KB1, JUN, TBKBP1, and p21 (CDKN1A), with a PPI enrichment <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value of 2.47&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10&#8315;&#8309;, indicating that these genes are more interconnected than expected by chance (Supplementary Fig.&#160;1). Notably, MTOR and TBK1 emerged as central nodes, suggesting convergence between mTORC1 signaling and immune-regulatory pathways, consistent with their known roles in tumor growth and inflammation. The KEGG pathway analysis further identified enrichment in the insulin resistance and mTOR signaling pathways, linking metabolic dysregulation to oncogenic signaling in breast cancer (Supplementary Fig.&#160;2).</p><p id="Par39">Although peripheral blood represents an indirect source of tumor-related gene expression and may be influenced by systemic and immune factors, it still serves as a meaningful medium for detecting molecular changes linked to breast cancer development and progression. Studies have demonstrated that blood-derived gene expression profiles can serve as meaningful indicators of disease presence and immune status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Studies emphasized that the peripheral blood transcriptome can capture immune-related biomarkers relevant to disease subtypes, including TNBC, thereby supporting its role in personalized and minimally invasive biomarker discovery. A study reported that gene expression patterns in peripheral blood mononuclear cells of breast cancer patients differ significantly from those of healthy individuals, highlighting distinct immune-related signaling pathways associated with tumor progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Future studies using larger, prospective cohorts will incorporate receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis, AUC estimation, and survival data to establish clinical relevance and diagnostic performance of the identified targets. Although mRNA-based profiling cannot fully capture the post-transcriptional or functional dynamics of signaling pathways, it nonetheless provides a meaningful foundation for identifying candidate genes and pathways of interest. Subsequent studies incorporating protein-level validation and functional assays will be essential to confirm these transcriptomic findings and to better define their biological implications in breast cancer.</p><p id="Par40">The consistent overexpression of PRKCQ and its downstream effectors across subtypes and in patients with positive family history emphasizes its potential as a central oncogenic driver in breast cancer. The observed crosstalk between PRKCQ and the mTORC1 complex via TBK1, and its additional activation of JUNB integrates signaling from both metabolic and transcriptional regulation pathways. The parallel downregulation of p21, a known checkpoint regulator, may enhance the oncogenic potential of this pathway bypassing tumor-suppressive mechanisms. Together, these findings suggest that this PRKCQ-centered pathway could be contributing to both the initiation and progression of breast cancer. It may also serve as a useful diagnostic or therapeutic target, particularly in aggressive or treatment-resistant breast cancer subtypes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par41">This study highlights the significant upregulation of PRKCQ, TBK1, mTORC1, S6K, and JUNB in breast cancer patients, with the strongest expression observed in aggressive subtypes and advanced stages of the disease. These findings support the involvement of a PRKCQ&#8211;TBK1&#8211;mTORC1&#8211;S6K signaling axis, as well as a separate PRKCQ&#8211;JUNB-VEGFR axis, in breast cancer progression. Additionally, the marked downregulation of p21 reinforces its role as a tumor suppressor in breast cancer. The consistent overexpression of these oncogenic mediators across various clinicopathological features suggests their potential as biomarkers for disease severity and therapeutic targets. Further investigations are needed to validate these molecular interactions and assess their relevance in targeted breast cancer therapies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_MOESM1_ESM.png" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12885_2025_15352_MOESM2_ESM.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 2.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#8217;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors extend their appreciation to the Researchers Supporting project number (ORFFT-2025-131-1), King Saud University, Riyadh Saudi Arabia for funding this project.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>AH, MB, SZ, MS, YB, AA, SR, and TA designed the study, conceived the study and analyzed the results. AH, AK, MB, MS, YB, and SR conceived an initial part of the study, performed the experiment, and helped in compiling the results. AH, MB, SZ and MS experimented, AH, MS, JHT, YB, AK, SR, and TA helped in writing the results. AH, SR, TA, wrote the paper with input from all other authors MB, SZ, MS, YB, JHT, SR, and TA made a substantial contribution in the interpretation of data and revising the manuscript for intellectual content. All authors read and approved of the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors extend their appreciation to the Researchers Supporting project number (ORFFT-2025-131-1), King Saud University, Riyadh Saudi Arabia for funding this project. The funding body has no role in designing the study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this article.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par42">This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board (IRB No. 2024-IRB-A-14/14) of the Atta-ur-Rahman School of Applied Biosciences (ASAB), National University of Sciences and Technology (NUST). Informed consent was obtained from all study participants. The study was conducted in accordance with the ethical principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par43">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par44">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giaquinto</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer statistics, 2022</article-title><source>Cancer J Clin</source><year>2022</year><volume>72</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36190501</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Giaquinto AN, et al. Breast cancer statistics, 2022. Cancer J Clin. 2022;72(6):524&#8211;41.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36190501</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giaquinto</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer statistics 2024</article-title><source>Cancer J Clin</source><year>2024</year><volume>74</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39352042</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Giaquinto AN, et al. Breast cancer statistics 2024. Cancer J Clin. 2024;74(6):477&#8211;95.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3322/caac.21863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39352042</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chaudhari R, Patel V &amp; Kumar A. Cutting-edge approaches for targeted drug delivery in breast cancer: beyond conventional therapies. Nanoscale Adv. 2024;6(9):2270&#8211;86.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/d4na00086b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11059480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38694472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Subedi R et al. Factors influencing the time to diagnosis and treatment of breast cancer among women in low-and middle-income countries: a systematic review. Breast. 2024;75:103714.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.breast.2024.103714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10973645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38522173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byerly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PRKCQ promotes oncogenic growth and anoikis resistance of a subset of triple-negative breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13058-016-0749-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27663795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5034539</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Byerly J, et al. PRKCQ promotes oncogenic growth and anoikis resistance of a subset of triple-negative breast cancer cells. Breast Cancer Res. 2016;18:1&#8211;11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27663795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13058-016-0749-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5034539</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belguise</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emerging function of PKCtheta in cancer</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>221</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom11020221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33562506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7915540</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Nicolle A, Zhang Y, Belguise K. The emerging function of PKCtheta in cancer. Biomolecules. 2021;11(2):221.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33562506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biom11020221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7915540</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TBKBP1 and TBK1 form a growth factor signalling axis mediating immunosuppression and tumourigenesis</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>21</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41556-019-0429-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31792381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6901116</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Zhu L, et al. TBKBP1 and TBK1 form a growth factor signalling axis mediating immunosuppression and tumourigenesis. Nat Cell Biol. 2019;21(12):1604&#8211;14.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31792381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41556-019-0429-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6901116</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PKC&#952;-JunB axis via upregulation of VEGFR3 expression mediates hypoxia-induced pathological retinal neovascularization</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>325</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-020-2522-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7206019</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Kumar R, et al. PKC&#952;-JunB axis via upregulation of VEGFR3 expression mediates hypoxia-induced pathological retinal neovascularization. Cell Death Dis. 2020;11(5):325.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41419-020-2522-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7206019</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breast cancer classification: a review</article-title><source>Int J Health Sci Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.52403/ijhsr.20221018</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Das D. Breast cancer classification: a review. Int J Health Sci Res. 2022;12(10):140&#8211;9.</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular subtypes of triple-negative breast cancer: understanding of subtype categories and clinical implication</article-title><source>Genes Genomics</source><year>2020</year><volume>42</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13258-020-01014-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33145728</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Lee Y-M, et al. Molecular subtypes of triple-negative breast cancer: understanding of subtype categories and clinical implication. Genes Genomics. 2020;42(12):1381&#8211;7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33145728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13258-020-01014-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zengel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the clinicopathological features of invasive ductal, invasive lobular, and mixed (invasive ductal&#8201;+&#8201;invasive lobular) carcinoma of the breast</article-title><source>Breast Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12282-013-0489-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23925582</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Zengel B, et al. Comparison of the clinicopathological features of invasive ductal, invasive lobular, and mixed (invasive ductal&#8201;+&#8201;invasive lobular) carcinoma of the breast. Breast Cancer. 2015;22(4):374&#8211;81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23925582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12282-013-0489-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Association</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>World medical association declaration of helsinki: ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2013</year><volume>310</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>2191</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.281053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24141714</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Association WM. World medical association declaration of helsinki: ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects. JAMA. 2013;310(20):2191&#8211;4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24141714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1001/jama.2013.281053</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mering</surname><given-names>Cv</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STRING: a database of predicted functional associations between proteins</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC165481</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Mering Cv, et al. STRING: a database of predicted functional associations between proteins. Nucleic Acids Res. 2003;31(1):258&#8211;61.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12519996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkg034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC165481</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>36</volume><issue>suppl1</issue><fpage>D480</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkm882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2238879</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Kanehisa M, et al. KEGG for linking genomes to life and the environment. Nucleic Acids Res. 2007;36(suppl1):D480&#8211;4.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18077471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/nar/gkm882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2238879</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryzhakov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randow</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SINTBAD, a novel component of innate antiviral immunity, shares a TBK1-binding domain with NAP1 and TANK</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>3180</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17568778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1914091</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Ryzhakov G, Randow F. SINTBAD, a novel component of innate antiviral immunity, shares a TBK1-binding domain with NAP1 and TANK. EMBO J. 2007;26(13):3180&#8211;90.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17568778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/sj.emboj.7601743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1914091</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revach</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting TBK1 to overcome resistance to cancer immunotherapy.</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2023</year><volume>615</volume><issue>7950</issue><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-023-05704-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36634707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10171827</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Sun Y, Revach OY, Anderson S. Targeting TBK1 to overcome resistance to cancer immunotherapy. Nature. 2023;615(7950):158&#8211;67.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36634707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41586-023-05704-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10171827</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshitomi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Emerging role of AP-1 transcription factor JunB in angiogenesis and vascular development</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2804</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22062804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33802099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8000613</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Yoshitomi Y, et al. Emerging role of AP-1 transcription factor JunB in angiogenesis and vascular development. Int J Mol Sci. 2021;22(6):2804.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33802099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms22062804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8000613</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of CDKN1A/p21 and TGFBR2 in breast cancer and their prognostic significance</article-title><source>Int J Clin Exp Pathol</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>14619</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26823785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4713571</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Wei C-Y, et al. Expression of CDKN1A/p21 and TGFBR2 in breast cancer and their prognostic significance. Int J Clin Exp Pathol. 2015;8(11):14619.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26823785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4713571</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prvanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of PTEN, PI3K, and mTOR in triple-negative breast cancer</article-title><source>Life</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1247</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/life11111247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34833123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8621563</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Prvanovi&#263; M, et al. Role of PTEN, PI3K, and mTOR in triple-negative breast cancer. Life. 2021;11(11):1247.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34833123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/life11111247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8621563</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miricescu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PI3K/AKT/mTOR signaling pathway in breast cancer: from molecular landscape to clinical aspects</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>173</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22010173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33375317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7796017</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Miricescu D, et al. PI3K/AKT/mTOR signaling pathway in breast cancer: from molecular landscape to clinical aspects. Int J Mol Sci. 2020;22(1):173.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33375317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms22010173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7796017</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manousakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>
<italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A/p21 in Breast Cancer: Part of the Problem, or Part of the Solution?</italic>
</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>17488</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms242417488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38139316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10743848</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Manousakis E, et al. <italic toggle="yes">CDKN1A/p21 in Breast Cancer: Part of the Problem, or Part of the Solution?</italic> Int J Mol Sci. 2023;24(24):17488.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38139316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms242417488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10743848</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#268;ele&#353;nik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poto&#269;nik</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peripheral blood transcriptome in breast cancer patients as a source of less invasive immune biomarkers for personalized medicine, and implications for triple negative breast cancer</article-title><source>Cancers</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>591</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers14030591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35158858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8833511</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">&#268;ele&#353;nik H, Poto&#269;nik U. Peripheral blood transcriptome in breast cancer patients as a source of less invasive immune biomarkers for personalized medicine, and implications for triple negative breast cancer. Cancers. 2022;14(3):591.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35158858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cancers14030591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8833511</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression profile of peripheral blood mononuclear cells may contribute to the identification and immunological classification of breast cancer patients</article-title><source>Breast Cancer</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12282-018-0920-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30317464</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Suzuki E, et al. Gene expression profile of peripheral blood mononuclear cells may contribute to the identification and immunological classification of breast cancer patients. Breast Cancer. 2019;26(3):282&#8211;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30317464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12282-018-0920-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>